[
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Study the given pattern carefully and select the number that can replace the question mark (?) in it.</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-a15561cd-7fff-4a2e-e764-bfe96e4f7faa\"><img height=\"65\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcG01ZEb0LdKRAYLgq6bEyBe-Fks76J2SJdgGCDlrJZ06LOARX9oODkqm1ruElzj12rqN-KT62TP_AOJNinTN90wGsg-887v0E6YXyB-kBoF33-nq0Ag4BbObeDsO47082_w8642g?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"159\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>50</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>55</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>45</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>40</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Logic:</strong> in each row a, a<sup>2</sup> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">+ b, b</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Following the same l</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ogic : <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mn>5</mn><mn>2</mn></msup></math></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> + 20 = 25 + 20 = 45</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> The sequence of folding a piece of paper and the manner in which the folded paper has been cut is shown in the following figures. How would this paper look when unfolded?</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-b6cccca5-7fff-cd20-e6fd-8f56d6fef3b3\"><img height=\"65\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcTR_eKkPO6_EtLrKkLGnWfbiha3uy0ye9Qz19Z3Vc1n8YErwMeCqopyDfzvp2Ltu5BrUb0m9lWHbjmo4c1a0ydbgrorxCEKZeybVUIA7RqFWVfxeJKNA99Zl-LkOODaQzfiOu2ug?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"200\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-cec775b8-7fff-8730-399a-1d9778aa31ab\"><img height=\"70\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcQCwHL55X16v0nADhWmKzxR6ZtGoAmXTq5mhvAtgi3_meER6tQXZUjqZStGhEjz49d_A8Z1z_2DvjbpKpZ9PbAV_LxQ6kLgk8YuUH3B8W2cVLP3w3tIh8HvQ6NRfagKJgat950?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_2": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-ad8c3138-7fff-d252-3a61-80047cb86b5c\"><img height=\"69\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXe3bajSbIEg6cXnDkdbrG9bbc8BYQ_3A6QU3jmzR9pjPGxqo_DBpdTB5tGWE-6C_FlLK6mNhhzpO85t-V3xqfjwa-8cTkWRMiYkDLr9uNSHJDsfJfi1WuARQbWPC1VBQdmscu6_NA?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_3": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-23fb5fc5-7fff-c3d5-8419-49e9921b4ef6\"><img height=\"69\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeYNiMXltB4LTgbRk8Evy89qFpa4jzWcS25jbhniJjkqdo4ceLGN4bnAkDnCTgP3FdvoKaSuKXDYHIhf64WQORVIJl1CX-kxGlkhO_j3ez0a-1ihPoUxdKeefREufQ-tmVOxqWmwQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-3b8a6602-7fff-9bfa-2c2b-7c11e16f88c2\"><img height=\"69\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXfyA7e425qzwAw9ZSXsBwmLi2-PZzzaoeXuKrJ1n6dvsJEeoca1Jzl6ntR54bqUyAybvc31VOxd1V7jNlZv7BUci8J6YemFZHe1etQ2QylWZdhbnlZG0hN2d4CkzM1FI-sWfx92hg?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-23fb5fc5-7fff-c3d5-8419-49e9921b4ef6\"><img height=\"69\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeYNiMXltB4LTgbRk8Evy89qFpa4jzWcS25jbhniJjkqdo4ceLGN4bnAkDnCTgP3FdvoKaSuKXDYHIhf64WQORVIJl1CX-kxGlkhO_j3ez0a-1ihPoUxdKeefREufQ-tmVOxqWmwQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the option in which th</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">e numbers are related in the same way as are the numbers of the following set.</span><br/><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\">(4, 10, 53) </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>(5, 13, 62) </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>(11, 31, 152)</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>(7, 19, 98) </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>(8, 20, 103)</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Logic :</strong> a, 3a - 2 = b, 5b + 3</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Following the same pattern </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Option: (c), 7, 7 × 3 - 2 = 19 and 19 × 5 + 3 = 98 </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">7, 19, 98 is the correct answer.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the figure from among the given options that can replace the question mark(?) i</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">n the following series.</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-f01059ed-7fff-0f14-74ee-75be5e86e8eb\"><img height=\"63\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXecTwLwJIhQdm6PZatarjZY0s9Wu4s1k2PQ2jF0cig-A26ZK9FIqAlBlsZLiu4BDMO4UArTOCWviISArQOusYWoxSayU7S55KlfE6v3sJB3wIEIUnp2ZVorwr0LqtPOvsHJ1Qb_uQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"350\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-0d1c8db2-7fff-7fa6-4a0c-0743fd001acb\"><img height=\"70\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdfBaTmfsJa1yYn-SaHbJSJuewgMc-mO9rMyviBUPdRXmsknfNTBHvqE2mpiquHoR-Qog23lK9YDPrlU_Vbkyjlb8u6sXe7m7TUYZMdHKW7yuC-uJCLLDVlQMgGBR-yIhlYTH-6yQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_2": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-aa8a3e4f-7fff-dc5d-f983-395b6fe66752\"><img height=\"71\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeR0_-VcUz3J1RRDhuPBsk7nsQPq7DfJbz4uNnsqW8kF0Mg56gmh0WJzJOzlc4jErCM7CvZtjlQi35AJL35UQQqC1YRHVQoCKKM6nxl_sMMeBnj4O_GMrZWaZUvrqRjYYGEOAVKqg?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_3": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-1842e3f3-7fff-abf6-88a9-1c26afd71049\"><img height=\"70\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeExKNSD9AMbrCCBaCK49DqOMofU9yYy25cZDRonUwk3q2KWkxXSnkSkWeuX2954RqdIJ3MaUBvhyzSz3w8r7-l27nNNm1R4DuaLGtBN2WpKAD-OyI_6nUSbaBWn986Gzs8seMcoA?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-f8cf8b5c-7fff-d065-a4d1-90b9fc43bfcb\"><img height=\"70\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeUgzCzsnDwvIXgH4FsKMZXRYm1eoIlep0dQCc-1SkkcNxK86ND-lL8zQucoxqgvGfEvWwUJ0VnaYYvxe3kVBAJKK4B-OC08wXSs_sjRNtNa6XiVLzvsskIBXQVOXsdcrxpaGQjow?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-899b3b54-7fff-e983-b63d-cfeade18f49b\"><img height=\"70\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeExKNSD9AMbrCCBaCK49DqOMofU9yYy25cZDRonUwk3q2KWkxXSnkSkWeuX2954RqdIJ3MaUBvhyzSz3w8r7-l27nNNm1R4DuaLGtBN2WpKAD-OyI_6nUSbaBWn986Gzs8seMcoA?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Find the number of triangles in the given figure.</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-cbb69b23-7fff-ff7f-006b-1b2e82cd08da\"><img height=\"99\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdKPb0ZIA5ZkV-tWWOxvc5shoVqYgRXMj10442g9uMfpp15OcTdGiM678xcMJU23zWNH7lSJcpZMmziezVbNSDbQE8ewJEr5YUDkzUfUJALH5cMzfhe5e16qO97SsWKyIJ92nT-Cg?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"100\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>16</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>20</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>18</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>14</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-35d8bf98-7fff-5a73-bdc4-c7653ff6d6e1\"><img height=\"141\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdd9s2meJAqG6boD1op_m0ikRSOot4wguwn0rgVYh-SEo3wdmENlppJYbKfpCxKLAlFFL69fMCcZB382rLZsYXofyGuMaXWxazfiv-sBCnlvz9Fqey6rf0c-Msm-EE5g0ZoHkhl?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"120\"/></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Triangles are ABC, ADG, BDE, CFG, BHI, CJK, AHK, BP</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">L, CMQ, APQ, IMJ, ILM, JKM, KMQ, IMK, SDP, GRQ, CKM. Total 18 are present in the figure.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> In a certain code language, 'REFUSAL' is coded as '2101239103' and 'POETRY' is coded as '1067927'. How will 'PROFIT' be coded in that language? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>18216972 </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>12186792</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>21671829 </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>81217629</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">first arrange the all the letters in a</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">lphabetical order </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Single digit is multiplied by </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">2</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">and double digits are added</span><br/><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\">(A = 1 × 2 &amp; L = 1 + 2 = 3)</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">REFUSAL - AEFLRSU ( 2101239103)</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">PROFIT - FIOPRT (12186792)</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> The present age of Ramesh is 7 years more than the present age of his wife Sangeeta. 6 years <b>hence,</b> the age of Ramesh will be three times that of his son Mayank. If the present age of Mayank is 10 years, then what is the present age of Sangeeta? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>42 <span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">years </span></p>",
        "option_2": "<p>48 years</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>30 years </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>35 years</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Present age of Mayank = 10</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">6 years hence age of Mayank = 16</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">6 years hence age of Ramesh = 48</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Ramesh present age = 42</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Wife present age = 42 - 7 = 35</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the option in which the given figure is embedded (rotation is NOT allowed).</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-452dbfd9-7fff-0432-e0a7-74c9261a3ee5\"><img height=\"68\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdHcPRpXm8Wgll38ZN-YCNmG72jv4gfGn-P2FfExTB2hxvLlkQ_PoOJdcbYDnmgU4cE_TiYW1VIwxIZ6vnPBNKEmfNZqwEEWZcfKBSdnbk4bIKpPGfSWtUmbCP9G3mCbBUcL_OrqA?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"70\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-e811751a-7fff-3e44-7b81-ce338fc62415\"><img height=\"86\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXc3N1DdZod6ZDa8s5I2azJaQRBSMgEoGtAeyhpRd53OvvP5vO-UqjVrEgoPFTC-kNNODZkodiwBVU2g_ZF3uDD9rADxYle0Z4u1ccMd1O0vExBVDBTIsT-4wIWYilrOvolI4dda1A?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_2": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-5302eab2-7fff-8183-df41-cb840bb3e099\"><img height=\"84\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcUMkaY9ikNaR8yYYgEyFqwgE9wjSGv9CMxTg1dx__QBpuMTfInq2UF9_VOhx3lb3gk5HMFAMz9EFJI47F876IE9BrtHlQ8N-_AT1KDvc8hsXUNO9idThkrp0wFPepewaMOMTOUSQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_3": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-b076295e-7fff-ca7b-35f9-334fff7c0c31\"><img height=\"85\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXfMZCX0UNnmUeL-osV0gT5FqVFh1T4B5oKNPD8l893NWnW7nzaJxpZ9z9gao83NSauH0I7wH_751V2mpsk0yUoB-eyGjQzFiPLkQAYhdioklGFMZgcBkKja18jeMelSkZ3UVh3Wlw?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-5cb6e791-7fff-01ef-bf27-98433fc69e9e\"><img height=\"85\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeJJgR4aAnNyAkSVqHeMpMge623wVmDd0QTLmNYH-eaDVgeP28sMEzUDr_TiIEyPae_Mpt0EufK8O6O_313mCvs8ieHEDcDRJkfaG-cSzEcDdhF-MqN-Tyr6RHl3ifB_qx8MpidFQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-963588f4-7fff-0e0d-1735-f024eb1bee88\"><img height=\"84\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcUMkaY9ikNaR8yYYgEyFqwgE9wjSGv9CMxTg1dx__QBpuMTfInq2UF9_VOhx3lb3gk5HMFAMz9EFJI47F876IE9BrtHlQ8N-_AT1KDvc8hsXUNO9idThkrp0wFPepewaMOMTOUSQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the number from among the given options that can replace the question mark (?) in the following series.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">6, 6, 8, 24, 28, 140, ? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>145</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>148</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>146</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>144</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Logic :</strong> odd place number is obtained by multiplying by 1,3,5 and so on… and even place number is obtained by adding 1 to the number which is multiplied in the last step.140 is 5 times of 28 so adding 6 to it gives 146.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the option in which the words share the same relatio</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">nship as that shared by the given pair of words.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Jharkhand : Ranchi </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Sikkim : Itanagar</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Mizoram : Kohima</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Assam : Jorhat</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Meghalaya : Shillong</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">As Ranchi is the capital of Jharkhand in the same way Shillong is the capital of Meghalaya.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the letter-cluster from among the given options that can </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">replace </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">the question mark (?) in the following series.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">CUH, HQK, MMN, RIQ, ? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>UDS </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>WET</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>VGT </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>XFS</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Logic:</strong> +5, -4, +3 pattern is followed</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">R + 5 = W, I - 4 = E and Q + 3 = T </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">WET is the answer.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>12<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">. Select the letter from among the given options that can replace the question mark (?) in the following series. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">H, Q, I, T, K, ?, N </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Y </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>J</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>U </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>A</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">As, H × 2 + 1 = Q</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">I × 2 + 2 = T and in the same way K × 2 + </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">3 = Y</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the option that is related to the third word in the same way as the second word is related to the first word.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Circle : Arc :: Plant : ? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Stem </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Tree</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Chlorophyll </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Plasma</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">As, arc is a part of a circle in the same stem is the part of a Plant.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the correct combination of mathematical signs that can sequentially replace the * signs </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">and balance the equation.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">483 * 23 * 93 * 16 * 4 * 50 </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>÷, -, +, ×, = </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>+, ÷, -, ×, =</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>÷, +, -, =, × </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>÷, +, -, ×, =</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Using option d </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">483 ÷ 23 + 93 - 16 × 4 = 50 </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">21 + 93 - 64 = 50</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">50 = 50 is the correct answer.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Three different positions of the same dice are shown. The faces of which are marked the letters A, B, C, D, E a</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">nd F. Select the letter that will be on the face opposite to the face having the letter 'D'.</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-ce6482a3-7fff-7485-ea46-7d21d3c15635\"><img height=\"75\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdHl80kwpDYA_xbkBgxFX4J7CfKBUPY49WlTzvZlVZ4NYCmIs1bnz-ffALwZFikyrzHXtjUOJXAW7gcwvXTRhp1WxV1dvBr1jVlBLgm8OcEcVF-n8cW0tBvw1MFNv59SEcPEdMa?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"180\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>A</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>C</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>B</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>F</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">From dice 1 and 3 B is common and D is missing so they both are opposite to each other.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Read the given statements and conclusions carefully. Ass</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">uming that the information given in the statements is true, even if it appears to be at variance with commonly known facts, decide which of the given conclusions logically follow(s) from the statements.</span><br/><strong><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Statements:</span></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Some mats are carpets. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Some carpets ar</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">e blankets. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">No blanket is a quilt. </span><br/><strong><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Conclusions: </span></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">I. No quilt is a carpet. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">II. No blanket is a mat. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">III. Some carpets are mats. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Only conclusion III follows</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Only conclusion II follows</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Both conclusions I and III follow</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Only conclu<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">sion I follows </span></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-b75e833e-7fff-2971-8c25-a294ffb35a77\"><img height=\"46\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcu8CY1xz1-nG8hvuwXFWJsrC711oIPqes6ANl-nVT_Zj72vYeQKzXtLVfQ-6uLkzF8uJjGjZ5GtUL8WfGw57ySUH3VSrt5up1q87ueOooEbGOV8BYdZ_z0rxmUoU10lEzhOAFG?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"250\"/></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Some carpets are mats is clearly visible so, it is true else other conclusions are false.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the correct option that indicates the arrangement of the given words in the order in which they appear in an English dictionary.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">1. Gravity </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">2. Glycogen </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">3. Gestation </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">4. Glycerine </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5. Ges</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ture </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>3, 1, 2, 4, 5 </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>3, 5, 2, 4, 1</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>3, 5, 4, 2, 1 </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>3, 2, 5, 1, 4</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The correct dictionary order is: 3, 5, 4, 2 ,1</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Gestation </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">→ Gestrue → Glycerine → Glycogen → Gravity</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Four letter-clusters have been given, out of which three are alike in some manner and one is different. Selec</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">t the letter-cluster that is different. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>XZTB </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>BDYF</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>TVQX </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>NPKR</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Logic:</strong> +2, -5, +7 is the pattern followed</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">But in XZTB, Z - 5 = U (not T)</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the option that is related to the third number in the same way as the second number is related to the first number and the sixth number is related to the fifth number.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">16 : 8 :: 21 : ? :: 11 : 6 </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>14</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>11</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>9</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>10</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<br/><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\">16 : 8 ⇒ 16 + 4 = 20 ; 20</span><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\"> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>÷</mo></math> 5 = 4 and 4 × 2 = 8 </span><br/><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\">21 : 10 ⇒ 21 + 4 = 25 ; 25 <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>÷</mo></math></span><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\"> 5 = 5 and 5 × 2 = </span><strong>10</strong><br/><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\">11 : 6 ⇒ 11 + 4 = 15 ; 15 </span><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>÷</mo></math> 5 = 3 and 3 × 2 = 6</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Four number-pairs have been given, out of which three are alike in some manner and one is different. Select the number-pair that is different. (Any operation on digits is not allowed) </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>326 : 107</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>308 : 101</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>197 : 66</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>239 : 78</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Logic:</strong> 3a + 5 : a</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">But option c does not follow this logic </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">As 66 × 3 + 5 = 203 (Not 197)</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Four words have been given, out of which three are alike in some manner and one is different. Select the word that is different. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Devotion </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Zeal</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Vision </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Fury</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Except vision other three are feelings but vision is a ability to see </span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> In a certain code language, 'VIRTUE' is written as 'DBZBNX'. How will 'OMINOUS' be written in that language? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>HBUVHNA </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>HUBVHNA</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>IBUHABM </p>",
        "option_4": "<p>IUBHM<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">BA </span></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Logic :</strong> Vowel is coded as -7 and consonant is coded as +8.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">So, O is O - 7 = H, I - 7 =B, U - 7 = N and consonants M + 8 = U, N + 8 = V, S + 8 = A</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Code for OMINOUS is HUBVHNA.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Select the correct mirror image of the given figure when the mirror is placed at 'AB' as shown.</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-192db941-7fff-c723-e73c-3b26aa712d53\"><img height=\"115\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXesCc7K6WEcAY13DzgIfaQ8HYZxDGsjZup9shSLKaxR_VRUXH7XLEnBphS6crqTO_wggazYYUsVwZsFQ98AJRZlCnuMRRidRnIBXMdjBYe5ZpvG91Ze8NJCKYid1aapuL561JmI?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-ab891fe4-7fff-07d3-6022-9466030f5ed8\"><img height=\"90\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXd9pwE2gjgnp_Ya3Gwv0EFCPTLwHIpo_-mdg58q2LjsgDSrCbkBy-ZIYpdHGEKpbp2I7UhRzezLAV_ww-4_c5H9zMOWI4ZgatNvqxRBALKn3klRNJackVNb1YquNJUcHlZ5FXXUYQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_2": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-5c38d79f-7fff-4cad-7726-551d2b7ea651\"><img height=\"87\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXd03BbGGtrWOyAlBmgIch53co5HZ9k1Sqql86dVz_4eVZOSvWOFmyWVoWymkHl-PFveVIMOHAKcjAP_8272wY80387jK-b1gceOG-mglUju4g7WxAA4hwpp83Tp4qIFRgODEjcvpg?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_3": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-2414c3bc-7fff-810a-61cc-7aae642359d6\"><img height=\"86\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXc43mDFP2YQs3zj4fTgHYG0ISNxJ4Kohe1sWmm7UlK9_7LdzN1JYWKgWvo3DqQvXpcrFdB4FUQ_PiA9y-HUgl1BUmLiWbJssPtILbznGSHlN5rdRWFaZK19xg9doTTV5ZXYphce3Q?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-1cfc35cf-7fff-b475-6f04-788a9067027d\"><img height=\"86\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeT7SOC_eMDzBtmPY7ld9PAJA_ItVXxCEV5AhwFjEUzPc46MYtvPpDTz9rx3VeZJ8OQY13gL2I8QMaHemhsVQ1DhKDwveYBlhGwftWyZCD2MYgPUwhGySjbPEAAzplctMcoMh_0qA?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"90\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-b99e1b60-7fff-b955-e1fe-48dfb43163b3\"><img height=\"119\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeg3cBLYaaFD-WsLow5lMSvRlivSEAFiVjp8sSVhz-N1NZU5_h-5tUxiY4_-csqncEhBZ3i3vifE1Xtae0GtoaGAjLakHJQDtCxAoc5c5LLBExRWz15WdvL-0xM9DNnnr0BlMvXow?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"180\"/></strong></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Rani is the sister of Piyush and the daughter of Kamal. Kamal is the son of Gaurav and the brother of Aryan. Aryan is the father of Rajneesh. How is Aryan related to Piyush ? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Brother</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Paternal Grandfather</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Paternal Uncle</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Father</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-39966f29-7fff-367f-c9a4-bec1d3f87379\"><img height=\"121\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXe1su6Fb8omCfpXjkWNbBe51olh__qhs0k5iXupZyBUUsDIyOooAtlGQOV5Iw7km1paRNhuF-msnfcCYdDXQwnyexGlYsOHtlwdewO_wFM0e5Vif31y9Y_Yw4F-TK8Yq1fpg79H6A?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"250\"/></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">From the family tree Aryan is Piyush’s fath</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">er Kamal's brother so, Aryan is Paternal uncle of Piyush. </span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Select the Venn diagram that best illustrates the relationship among the following classes.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Nept</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">une, Planet, Moon</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-b3e0f691-7fff-0b6e-629d-360b2603f931\"><img height=\"58\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXctCW92pTYVdZeyo3TWJzXas_s00XdI5wYY55yPDePQN9XbgC86a7ZjTupiUMhr7rLPUSAd69LuG7XsozMtvAPNDa0KIXXwTqYh9m9qKXn9-PZ9jITYxFy61imnJCGaBEJt4gCLYg?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"150\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_2": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-0d477e77-7fff-4fe7-a816-e29cbfad8336\"><img height=\"84\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXc--x32dhx_JCuVXsmd_KE-sX_96B2f5zN-z0c3FBsQcZjezOSxfB-QMxj6c-iElo_o8-MVxEWQuoNqP00c9PuQ8Q-cw-7CGW7Y7f8fErCgI7DGVVPkb3693bcH8KPRHpwaVrehBQ?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"150\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_3": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-a0043e89-7fff-82c1-94f2-d76260a54ae6\"><img height=\"90\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcALcKHAkjvhxRZpdqyl8AZ4Z7CeszWyUR1tcS8IWhNDukFX3XpgOxnegsZPlu2nE5eo-yZyo9jkf57UKYoLWCsLPzkEeuIKdEiWGB-1_e6jOQie9_UQAUSud9f4A4zdoh6bQTyXA?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"120\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-a1ebba22-7fff-fe2a-740b-89b723856401\"><img height=\"102\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdVHf2xkRXM9IsUNfeIEmUBgM5UaOQb8woAe7qE7fqB1Gb4edGXGOrHFBsSFsWnNZW4OUsldF7DzTHIReOVJLQIfWDGEpwj_hAsrVOlWjwDZT2_RM5FoYXDARjUiE71x1Tc6SOlaw?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"100\"/></strong></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Neptune is a planet whereas moon</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> is neither a planet nor does it has any relation with moon.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Which of the following is a coarse grained igneous rock that contains quartz and feldspar<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Granite</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Basalt</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Marble</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Andesite</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) Granite is a coarse grained igneous rock that contains quartz and feldspar and plagioclase.<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> It forms from magma with a high content of silica and alkali metal oxides that slowly cools and solidifies underground.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>In which<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> of the following Indian states will you find the ‘Kunchikal Falls’? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Kerala</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Karnataka</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Tamil Nadu</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Telangana</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) ‘Kunchikal Falls’ is formed on Varahi river in Karnataka. It is located in Nidagodu village near Masthikatte in Shimoga district of Karnataka.<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The height of this majestic waterfa</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ll is 455 mt (1,493 ft) making it the highest waterfall in India.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>The total membership of the Constituent Assembly was 389, of which ______ were representatives of princely states.</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>84</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>102</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>109</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>93</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>28<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">.(d) The total membership of the Constituent Assembly was 389, of which</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> 292 were representatives of the provinces, 93 represented the princely states and 4 were from the chief commissioner provinces of Delhi, Ajmer-Merwara, Coorg and British Baluchistan.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Who among the following was the first Finance Minister of Independent India?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>KC Neogy</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>CD Deshmukh</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>RK Shanmukham Chetty</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Liaquat Ali Khan</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) RK Shanmukham Chetty was the first finance minister of Independent India when the country's first budget was tabled in Parliament on 26 November 1947.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>According to Malthusian theory which of the following grows in geometric progression?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Poverty</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Employment</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Population</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Food supply</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) According to Malthusian theory, the population grows in geometr<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ic progression. This theory, proposed by Malthus who, stated that the human population increases geometrically, while food production increases arithmetically. Under this paradigm, humans would eventually be unable to produce enough food to sustain themselv</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">es.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>When we cut an onion, the vegetable emits an odour and our eyes tear up. Which of the following compounds is responsible for the tears and odour resulting from freshly cut oni<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ons? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Citric acid</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Ascorbic acid</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Acetic acid</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Sulphuric acid</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) Sulphuric acid is responsible for the tears and odour resulting from freshly cut onions.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>______ is the pattern of veins in the blade of a leaf.</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Anthology</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Morphology</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Cytology</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Venation</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) Venation is the pattern of veins in the blade of a leaf.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Who among the following became the co-chair of 17th ASEAN-India Summit in November 2020?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>The Chief Justice of India</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>The President of India</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>The Speaker of the Lok Sabha</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>The P<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">rime Minister of India </span></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) The Prime Minister of India became the co-chair of 17th ASEAN-India Summit in November 2020.<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The summit focused on measures to recover from the economic turmoil triggered by the Covid-19 pandemic and ways to further broad-base strategic</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> ties.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Which of the following states’ tourism ministry announced the launch of India’s first<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Labour Movement Museum in January 2021? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Kerala</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>West Bengal</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Odisha</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Karnataka</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) Kerala tourism ministry ann<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ounced the launch of India’s first Labour Movement Museum in Alappuzha in January 2021. The museum will feature a huge repository of documents and exhibits that shaped the labour movements across the continents.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Who has been re-appointed as the MD and CEO of the<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> RBL Bank in January 2021 for three years? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Rajeev Ahuja</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Vishwavir Ahuja</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Deepak Ruiya</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Rajeev Arora</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) Vishwavir Ahuja has been re-appointed as the MD and CEO of the RBL Bank in January 2021 for three years.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Who among the following Indian actors was honoured with the ‘Best Actor’ award at the Indo-German Film week held in Europe in 2020?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Shah Rukh Khan</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Adil Hussain</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Salman Khan</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Sanjay Dutt</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) Adil Hussain was honoured with the ‘Best Actor’ award at the Indo-German Film week held in Europe in 2020. He<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> is an Indian actor who has worked in Indian cinema, inc</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">luding art house cinema and mainstream Bollywood, as well as international cinema, in films such as The Reluctant Fundamentalist and Life of Pi. </span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Who among the following established the Rashtrakuta Kingdom?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Krishna I</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Dantidurga</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Ashoka</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Amoghavarsha</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) Dantivarman or Dantidurga (735 – 756) was the founder of the Rashtrakutas dynasty. Rashtrakuta<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">s were originally known to be the feudatories of the Western Chalukyas of Vatapi. They ruled from Manyakheta in Karnataka.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>In which of the following years was the Indian Independence Act passed by the British Parliament?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>1945</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>1942</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>1946</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>1947</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) The Indian Independence Act was passed by the British Parliament in 1947. The Act received Royal Assent on 18 July 1947 and thus India and Pakistan, comprising West (modern day Pakistan) and East (modern day Bangladesh) regions, came into being<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> on 15th August.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>What was the name of the first artificial satellite launched by India in 1975 ?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Panini</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Sushruta</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Aryabhatta</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Charaka</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) Aryabhatta was the name of the first artificial satellite launched by India in 1975.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>In which of the following states is Kolleru Lake located?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Madhya Pradesh</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Kerala</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Andhra Pradesh</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Tamil Nadu</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) Kolleru Lake is located in Andhra Pradesh. It is one of the largest freshwater lakes in<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> India. </span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>SP Balasubramaniam was a ______ who was conferred with the Padma Vibhushan posthumously in January 2021.</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>singer</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>archaeologist</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>painter</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>scientist</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) SP Balasubramaniam<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">was an Indian </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">playback</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> singer, </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">television presenter, music director, actor and film producer who worked predominantly in Telugu, Tamil, Kannada, Hindi</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> and Malayalam films. He</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> was conferred with the Padma Vibhushan posthumously in January 2021. </span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Which of the following acids is used in the purification of gold and silver?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Maleic acid</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Formic acid</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Acetic acid</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Nitric acid</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) Nitric acid is used in the purification of gold and silver since it dissolves the impurities like various metal oxides present on the surface of gold. Gold is insoluble in HNO<sub>3</sub>.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Which of the following states inaugurated its first bird festival ‘Kalrav’ in January 2021?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Assam</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Bihar</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Tripura</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Odisha</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) Bihar Chief Minister Nitish Kumar inaugurated its first bird festival ‘Kalrav’ in January 2021. It was organised at Nagi-Nakti bird sanctuary, located in Jamui district, Bihar.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Which of the following states launched the scheme ‘Sujal - Drink from Tap Mission’ that aims to provide quality drinking<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">water directly from tap to all households in urban areas? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Odisha</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Uttar Pradesh</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>West Bengal</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Bihar</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) Odisha has launched the scheme ‘Sujal - Drink from Tap Mission’.<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The scheme will help pre</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">vent the generation of 400 metric tonnes of plastic waste since visitors to the city would no longer need to carry plastic bottles around and can drink water directly from the 400 fountains set up in the city, 120 of them on the Grand Road (where the famou</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">s Rath Yatra takes place) alone.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Makaravilakku is an annual festival held on Makar Sankranti in which of the following states?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Karnataka</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Tamil Nadu</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Kerala</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Odisha</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) Makaravilakku is an annual festival held on Makar Sankranti in Kerala at the shrine of Sabarimala. The festival includes the Thiruvabharanam (sacred ornaments of Lord Ayyappan) procession and a congregation at the hill shrine of Sabarim<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ala.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>What was the name of the wome<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">n's regiment in the Indian National Army founded by Subhash Chandra Bose? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Rani of Jhansi Regiment</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Rani Ahilyabai Regiment</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Rani Padmawati Regiment</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Rani of Didda Regiment</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) Rani of Jhansi Regiment was the<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">name of the women's regiment in the Indian National Army founded by Subhash Chandra Bose.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>In which of the following countries was<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> the headquarters of the International Olympic Committee located as of February 2021? </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>The US</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Switzerland</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>China</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Japan</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) The headquarters of the International Olympic Committee<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> are located in Switzerland as of February 2021. The International Olympic Committee (IOC) has inaugurated its new CHF145-million headquarters in the Swiss city of Lausanne. The inauguration coincided with the 125th anniversary of the organization which is</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> preparing to select the host city for the 2026 Winter Olympics.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Who was appointed as the middle and long-distance coach of the Indian athletics team in January 2021?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Adille Sumariwalla</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Radhakrishnan Nair</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Amrish Kumar</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Nikolai Snesarev</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) Nikolai Snesarev was appointed as the middle and long-distance coach of the Indian athletics team. Snesarev coached 10,000m runners Preeja Sreedharan and K<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">avita Raut in the 2010 Asian Games and steeplechaser Sudha Singh to gold.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>On which of the following days is National Disaster Response Force Raising Day celebrated annually?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>21 September</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>23 October</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>19 January</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>6 March</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) National Disaster Response Force came into existence on January 19, 2006. NDRF celebrates its r<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">aising day annually on 19 January. This year it celebrated its 16th anniversary.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Which of the following Articles of the Constitution of India defines for a separate secretarial staff for each House of the Parliament?</p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Article 98</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Article 123</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Article 155</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Article 34</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) Articles 98 of the Constitution of India defines a separate secretarial staff for each House of the Parliament.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">In a right angled triangle ABC, the lengths of the sides containing the right angle are 5 cm and 12 cm respectively. A circle is inscribed in the triangle ABC. What is the radius of the circle (in cm) ?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>8</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>3</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>2</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>2<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">.5</span></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Hypotenuse = </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> <span style=\"font-weight: 400;\"> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msqrt><msup><mn>12</mn><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mn>5</mn><mn>2</mn></msup></msqrt></math> </span></span><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\">= </span><span style=\"font-family: 'Cambria Math';\">13</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Inradius = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">P</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">B</mi><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">H</mi></mrow><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>12</mn><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mn>5</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mn>13</mn></mrow><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= 2</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The average daily production of toys in a factory in the month of December is 512. If the average production during the first 20 days is 515 and that of the last 13 days is 510, then what is the average of production on 19 and 20 December ?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>1058</p>",
        "option_2": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> 529</span></p>",
        "option_3": "<p>513</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>512</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Total production of toys in December = 512 <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>×</mo></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">31 = 15872</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Production of toys in first 20 days = 20 <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>×</mo></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">515 = 10300</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Production of toys in the last 13 days = 13 <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>×</mo></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">510 = 6630</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Production on 19th and 20th december is common in both the first 20 days and last 13 days.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Production on 19 and 20 December = 10300 + 6630 - 15872 = 1058 </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">So, Average of 19 and 20 = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>1058</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= 529</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A T.V. is sold at 8% gain. Had it been sold for Rs.2553 less; there would have loss of 15%. To gain 18%, the selling price (in Rs.) of T.V. would be: </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>11100</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>13098</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>15000</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>9102</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Let C.P. = 100%</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">S.P. at 8% ga</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">in = 108%</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">S.P. at 15% loss = 85%</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Difference = 108% - 85% = 23%</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">S.P. at 18% gain = 118%</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A/Q</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">23% ------- 2553</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">118% ------- 13098</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">S.P of T.V. at 18% gain = 13098</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A shopkeeper bought a machine for Rs.4600 and spent Rs.500 on its repairs and transp</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ort. He marked the machine at 8% above the overall cost price. If he sold the machine for Rs.4681.80 after giving x% discount, then the value of x is:</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>18</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>15</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>20</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>12</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Cost price = 4600</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Overall cost price = 460</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">0 + 500 = 5100</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">M.R.P = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>108</mn><mn>100</mn></mfrac></math> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>×</mo></math></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5100 = 5508</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Discount = 5508 - 4681.8 = 826.2</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">x% =</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mo> </mo><mn>826</mn><mo>.</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow><mn>5508</mn></mfrac></math> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>×</mo></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">100 = 15%</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Study the table and answer the question.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The table shows the daily income of 50 persons.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-be277c9e-7fff-659a-74a1-a34ccb3ef440\"><img height=\"121\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXctaM3ppF8PrG21MUzy0h54XF7n1EueB16VTkePu0F02WVxhUyiNVNlb_ttvwd4-3eMoxixfdM4rcvs-wLbNZ-VvfXVE0w-93BvIpyp6ohOMbJD5IBzkAfFrWBR7yLuXqfeJUjz?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"300\"/></strong></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">How many people earn Rs.250 or more but less than Rs.350 daily?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>28</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>24</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>14</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>18</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Number of persons = </span><span style=\"font-weight: 400;\">(34 - 26) + (40 - 34) = 8 + 6 = 14</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">If a</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">³</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> - b</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">³</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> = 2349 and (a - b) = 9, then (a + b)</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">²</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> - ab is equal to:</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>261</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>280</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>229</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>244</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) a³ - b³ = 2349<br/>(a - b) (a<sup>2 </sup>+ b<sup>2 </sup>+ ab) = 2349<br/>(a<sup>2</sup> + b<sup>2</sup> + ab) = 261<br/>(a + b)² - ab = a<sup>2 </sup>+ b<sup>2</sup> + ab = 261</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> If sin(A + B) = 1 and cos(A - B) =</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><msqrt><mn>3</mn></msqrt><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">, A + B ≤ 90° and A &gt; B, then the value of</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>5</mn><mi>sin</mi><mo>²</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">B</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mn>4</mn><mo> </mo><mi>tan</mi><mo>²</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">A</mi></mrow><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>sinB</mi><mo>.</mo><mi>cosA</mi></mrow></mfrac></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">is:</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>20</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>5</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>18</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>5</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">sin(A + B) = 1</span><br/>(A + B) = 90° ------ (1)<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">cos(A - B) = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><msqrt><mn>3</mn></msqrt><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></span><br/>(A - B) = 30° ----- (2)<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">From eq.(1) and (2)</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A = 60°, B = 30°</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>5</mn><mi>sin</mi><mo>²</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">B</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mn>4</mn><mi>tan</mi><mo>²</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">A</mi></mrow><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>sinB</mi><mo>.</mo><mi>cosA</mi></mrow></mfrac></math></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">⇒ <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>5</mn><mi>sin</mi><mo>²</mo><mn>30</mn><mo>°</mo><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mn>4</mn><mi>tan</mi><mo>²</mo><mn>60</mn><mo>°</mo></mrow><mrow><mn>2</mn><mi>sin</mi><mo> </mo><mn>30</mn><mo>°</mo><mo>.</mo><mo> </mo><mi>cos</mi><mo> </mo><mn>60</mn><mo>°</mo></mrow></mfrac></math></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">⇒ <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>5</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mstyle displaystyle=\"true\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo></mrow><mn>4</mn></mfrac></mstyle><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mn>4</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mn>3</mn></mrow><mrow><mn>2</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mstyle displaystyle=\"true\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></mstyle><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mstyle displaystyle=\"true\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></mstyle></mrow></mfrac></math></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">⇒ <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mstyle displaystyle=\"true\"><mfrac><mn>53</mn><mn>4</mn></mfrac></mstyle><mstyle displaystyle=\"true\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></mstyle></mfrac></math> = </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>53</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> = </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">26.5</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A sum of money was lent in two parts in the ratio 4 : 5 and 4 years and 5 years respectively, both at the rate of 8% per annum simple interest. If the difference between the interests earned from the two parts is Rs.4680, then what was the total sum lent (</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">in Rs.)</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>58500</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>46800</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>65000</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>42120</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Let, the total sum = 900</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Principal of 1st part = 400</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Principal of 2nd part = 500</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Simple interest on first part = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>400</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mn>8</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mn>4</mn></mrow><mn>100</mn></mfrac></math></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= 128</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Simple interest on 2nd part = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>500</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mn>8</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mn>5</mn></mrow><mn>100</mn></mfrac></math></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= 200</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Difference = 200 - 128 = 72</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A/Q</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">72 ------- 4680</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">900 ------- 58500</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> If a train runs with the speed of 72 km/h, it reaches its destination late by 15 minutes. However, if its speed is 90 km/h, it is late by only 5 minutes. The correct time to cover its journey in minutes is:</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>32 </p>",
        "option_2": "<p>40</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>45</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>35</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Ratio of speed :</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> 72 </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">: </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">90</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> 4 </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">: </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Ratio of time :</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> 5 </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">: </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">4</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Difference = 10 minutes</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">1 unit ------ 10 minutes</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5 unit ------ 50 minutes</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Correct time = 50 - 15 = 35</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">If x - <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mi>x</mi></mfrac></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msqrt><mn>77</mn></msqrt></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> then one of the values of x</span><sup><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">3</span></sup><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> + <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>3</mn></msup></mfrac></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">is:</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>-702</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>77√77</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>3√77</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>80√77</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><msqrt><mn>77</mn></msqrt></math><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Squaring both side</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mfrac></math> = 77 + 2</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mfrac></math> + 2 = 79 + 2</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi></mfrac></math> = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>±</mo><mn>9</mn></math></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Cubing both side</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>3</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>3</mn></msup></mfrac></math> = 729 - 27 = 702</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Or</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>3</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>3</mn></msup></mfrac></math> = -729 + 27 = -702</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Points A and B are on a circle with centre O. Point C is one the major arc AB. If ∠OAC = 35° and ∠OBC = 45°, then what is the measure (in degrees) of the angle subtended by the minor arc AB at the centre?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>80</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>70 </p>",
        "option_3": "<p>100</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>160</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-c9cf3256-7fff-a2f2-1f21-940f41378c4f\"><img height=\"144\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdP9gWlQ2R702BHw9ri3JBu-j6ETqCBwocgiYXv_4XApI1R6HLqfv37mYYfMr50Jn_5a24hrcVSktkdTVIXMbJ8uGPlnMShC5hTO0Dg-VcmOQKkLNbViaQ4Uuc7XL8197656pSnpA?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"130\"/></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">∠OCA = ∠OAC = 35°</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">∠OCB = ∠OBC = 45°</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">∠ACB = 35° + 45° = 80°</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">∠AOB = 2 × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">80° = 160°</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> If a number P is divisible by 2 and another number Q is divisible by 3, then which of the following is true?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>P × Q is divisible by 6</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>P + Q is divisible by 6</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>P + Q is divisible by 5</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>P × Q is divisible by 5</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">P = 2x, Q = 3y</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">P × Q = 6xy</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">6xy is divisible by 6</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">P × Q is also divisible by 6</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">P + Q = 2x + 3y</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">2x + 3y is not divisible by 5</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">So, P + Q is not divisible by 5</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Alternatively, put the value of P &amp; Q</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> In a circle with centre O, AB and CD are parallel chords on the opposite sides of a diameter. If AB = 12 cm, CD = 18 cm and the distance between the chords AB and CD is 15 cm, then find the radius of the circle (in cm).</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>3√13</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>9</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>9√<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">13 </span></p>",
        "option_4": "<p>12</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-2c799b75-7fff-bc0e-bfd7-a5ba388460c7\"><img height=\"111\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXf24o0DOX_2mNZTe6yT0f7a5kr_Je-EZQ0TjuIsKoGu2OZUTDYz34Zp45hVID9QcBYUJH7jJ5QFBtl6DJ4NvecxHuBoJAA-evdqbQ6vKqZKF2zeIPLYuOByf-7aNsjO2L4khbuq?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"120\"/></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">EF = 15 cm</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Let,OE = x</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">OF = 15 - x</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">OB = OD = r (radius)</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">AB = 12 cm, EB = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>12</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= 6 cm</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">CD = 18 cm, FD = 9 cm</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">In the right triangle OEB</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">r = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msqrt><msup><mn>6</mn><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></msqrt></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">------ (1)</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">In the right triangle OFD</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">r = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msqrt><msup><mn>9</mn><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>15</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup></msqrt></math></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">----- (2)</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">From eq (1) and (2)</span><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msqrt><msup><mn>6</mn><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></msqrt><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><msqrt><mo> </mo><msup><mn>9</mn><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><msup><mrow><mo> </mo><mo>(</mo><mn>15</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">x</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup></msqrt></math><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">36 + x² </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= 81 + 225 + x² </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">- 30x</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">30x = 270</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">x = 9</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">r = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msqrt><msup><mn>6</mn><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mn>9</mn><mn>2</mn></msup></msqrt></math></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msqrt><msup><mn>6</mn><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mn>9</mn><mn>2</mn></msup></msqrt><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><msqrt><mn>117</mn></msqrt></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= 3√13</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">If a + b + c = 0, then what is the value of</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">b</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">c</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mi>bc</mi></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">c</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">a</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mi>ca</mi></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">a</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">b</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mi>ab</mi></mfrac></math></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>1</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>-3</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>-1</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>3</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">a = 2,b = -1, c = -1</span><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">b</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">c</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mi>bc</mi></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">c</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">a</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mi>ca</mi></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">a</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">b</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mi>ab</mi></mfrac></math><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>-</mo><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mrow><mo>-</mo><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mo>-</mo><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mn>2</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mrow><mo>-</mo><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mn>2</mn></mrow></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mn>1</mn><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo></mrow><mrow><mn>2</mn><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mn>1</mn></mrow></mfrac></math><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">4 - <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">- <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> = </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">3</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The following table shows the daily seats occupancy in different classes of a train. Number of bracket represents the total seats available for a particular class.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-afbdfdc2-7fff-e97a-4083-018af6dd21d3\"><img height=\"120\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXf6QKsG_j2MMoDsNU9MgdlN90qdFZvAoXPk3xQctD-Se9dM2jxb0-ufPNZkUusuWB6KQx4deyCPK80THO8hx9DM2hMTUw15PwVYq5HwrOI4fPY1yCUu_ea5nvISKtwT3owZrHkn?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"500\"/></strong></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">What is the ratio of number</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> of seats that remained vacant in all the Non-AC classes on Wednesday and Thursday taken together to number of seats remained vacant in AC classes on Monday, Tuesday and Friday?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>35 : 62</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>62 : 35</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>39 : 62</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>62 : 39</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Number of seats remained vacant in all the Non-AC classes on Wednesday and Thursday = (900 - 830) + (500 - 390) + (900 - 790) + (500 - 480) </span><span style=\"font-family: 'Cambria Math';\">= 70 + 110 + 110 + 20 = 310</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Number of seats remained vacant in all the AC classes on Monday, Tuesd</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ay and Friday = (500 - 480) + (250 - 240) + (150 - 145) + (500 - 450) + (250 - 230) + (150 - 120) + (500 - 500) + (250 - 210) + (150 - 130) = 20 + 10 + 5 + 50 + 20 + 30 + 0 + 40 + 20 = 195</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Ratio = 310 : 195 = 62 : 39</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Find the value of <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>(</mo><mi>secθ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi>tanθ</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi>cosecθ</mi></mrow><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mi>cosecθ</mi></mrow></mfrac></math> where <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mn>0</mn><mo>°</mo><mo> </mo><mo>&lt;</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>&lt;</mo><mn>90</mn><mo>°</mo></math></span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>0</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>-2</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>1</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>2</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>(</mo><mi>secθ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi>tanθ</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi>cosecθ</mi></mrow><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mi>cosecθ</mi></mrow></mfrac></math><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>⇒</mo><mo> </mo><mo>(</mo><mi>secθ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi>tanθ</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>²</mo><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mi>cosecθ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi>cosec</mi><mrow><mn>2</mn><mo> </mo></mrow></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi></mrow></mfrac></math><br/>⇒ <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mi>sec</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi>tan</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mn>2</mn><mi>secθ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>×</mo><mo> </mo><mi>tanθ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi>cosec</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mn>2</mn><mi>cosecθ</mi><mo> </mo></mrow><mrow><mo>-</mo><msup><mi>cot</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi></mrow></mfrac></math><br/>⇒ sec<sup>2</sup>θ + tan<sup>2</sup>θ + 2secθ × tanθ - sec<sup>2</sup>θ - tan<sup>2</sup>θ - 2secθ × tanθ = 0</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Keshav, Surjeet and Thomas started a business with investments in the ratio 2 : 3 : 4. The ratio of their period of investments is 5 : 6 : 9. Twenty percent of the profit was spent on rent and maintenance of the office. Remaining profit was distributed amo</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ng themselves. If the difference in the share of profit of Keshav and Surjeet is Rs.7264 then how much is the total profit (in Rs.)?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>51060</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>58112</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>46490</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>72640</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Ratio of investments = 2 : 3 : 4</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Ratio of period = 5 : 6 : 9</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Ratio of profit =</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Keshav : Surjeet : Thomas</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">2 ×</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> 5 : 3 × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">6 : 4 × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">9</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> 10 : 18 : 36 </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> 5 : 9 : 18</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Difference of profit of Keshav and Surjeet = 9 - 5 = 4 unit</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Total share of profit = 5 + 9 + 18 = 32 unit</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A/Q</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">4 ------- 7264</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">32 ------- 58112</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Let total profit = 100%</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Profit shared = 80</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">%</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">80% ----- 58112</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">100% ----- 72640</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">If <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mi>sin</mi><mn>6</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi>cos</mi><mn>6</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac><mo>,</mo><mo> </mo><mn>0</mn><mo>°</mo><mo> </mo><mo>&lt;</mo><mo> </mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>&lt;</mo><mo> </mo><mn>90</mn><mo>°</mo><mo>,</mo></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">then what is th</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">e value of <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mi>sinθ</mi><mo>.</mo><mi>cosθ</mi></math> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><msqrt><mn>6</mn></msqrt><mn>6</mn></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_2": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><msqrt><mn>2</mn></msqrt><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_3": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><msqrt><mn>2</mn></msqrt><msqrt><mn>3</mn></msqrt></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>2</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mi>sin</mi><mn>6</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi>cos</mi><mn>6</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>(</mo><msup><mi>sin</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi>cos</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo>)</mo><mo> </mo><mo>[</mo><msup><mrow><mo>(</mo><msup><mi>sin</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><msup><mi>cos</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo>)</mo></mrow><mn>2</mn></msup><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mn>3</mn><msup><mi>sin</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo>.</mo><msup><mi>cos</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo>]</mo><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>[</mo><mn>1</mn><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mn>3</mn><msup><mi>sin</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo>.</mo><msup><mi>cos</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo>]</mo><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mn>3</mn><msup><mi>sin</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo>.</mo><msup><mi>cos</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>2</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><msup><mi>sin</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo>.</mo><msup><mi>cos</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">θ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>2</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac></math><br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>⇒</mo><mo> </mo><mi>sinθ</mi><mo>.</mo><mi>cosθ</mi><mo> </mo><mo>=</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mrow><mo>√</mo><mn>2</mn></mrow><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The given pie-chart shows the degree-wise breakup of expenditure of a family in a month. Total income of a family is Rs.43200.</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-a7105696-7fff-f451-05a1-816a8e0c5e59\"><img height=\"235\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdhZeemJ-0jITtHU0K9WQlnlfxLPK0BpPqHsAQPrpmoWZnqu6KlniKVF0MV9YqCnuHLA3nGnhiS3BAOqAoWUWfD8_iHEP5AXASOkwLljMCCTy-k-i0g9zgz9sZb44MAD_he8FLHfg?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"230\"/></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Expenditure on food is what percent more than expenditure on rent?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>200</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac><mo>%</mo></math></p>",
        "option_2": "<p>50%</p>",
        "option_3": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>50</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac><mo>%</mo></math></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>100</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac><mo>%</mo></math></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Degree of Expenditure on food = 105°</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Degree of Expenditure on rent = 70°</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Required percentage = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mn>35</mn><mo>°</mo></mrow><mrow><mn>70</mn><mo>°</mo></mrow></mfrac></math> ×</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">100 = 50%</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Five men can complete work i</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">n 20 days. Ten women can complete the same work in 15 days. Two men and six women started working together. After 5 days, three women left the work and a new man joined the work. The group continued working together till the end of the work. In how many da</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ys will they be able to do the remaining work?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>14</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>19</p>",
        "option_3": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mn>18</mn><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo> </mo><mn>16</mn><mfrac><mn>2</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Efficiency of Men = M</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Efficiency of Women = W</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A/Q</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5M × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">20 = 10W × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">15</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">M</mi><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">W</mi></mfrac></math> = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Efficiency of Men = 3</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Efficiency of Women = 2</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Total work = 5 × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">3 × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">20 = 300</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Work completed in 5 days = (2M + 6W) × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5 = 90</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Remaining work = 300 - 90 = 210</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Work in one day = 3M + 3W = 15</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Number of days = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>210</mn><mn>15</mn></mfrac></math></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">= 14</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Alloy A contains metal x and y in the ratio 5 : 2 and alloy B contains these metals in the ratio 3 : 4. Alloy C is prepared by mixing A and B in the ratio 4 : 5. The percentage of y in allo</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">y C is:</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mn>44</mn><mfrac><mn>4</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac></math>%</p>",
        "option_2": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo> </mo><mn>33</mn><mfrac><mn>4</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac></math>%</p>",
        "option_3": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mn>66</mn><mfrac><mn>4</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac><mo>%</mo><mo> </mo><mo> </mo><mo> </mo></math></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo> </mo><mn>55</mn><mfrac><mn>5</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac><mo>%</mo></math></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> X : Y</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> A </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">(5 : 2) × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">4</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">B </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">(3 : 4) × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">20 : 8</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">B </span><span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\"><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">15 : 20</span></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">C </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">35 : 28</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Percentage of Y = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>28</mn><mn>63</mn></mfrac></math> × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">100 = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mn>44</mn><mfrac><mn>4</mn><mn>9</mn></mfrac><mo>%</mo></math></span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Simplify the expression. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mn>441</mn><mo> </mo><mo>÷</mo><mo> </mo><mo>[</mo><mn>270</mn><mo> </mo><mo>÷</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>7</mn></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mo>(</mo><mn>17</mn><mo> </mo><mo>÷</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mo>(</mo><mn>8</mn><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>5</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mo>]</mo></math></span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>49</mn><mn>75</mn></mfrac><mo> </mo></math></p>",
        "option_2": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>39</mn><mn>75</mn></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_3": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>19</mn><mn>75</mn></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_4": "<p><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>29</mn><mn>75</mn></mfrac></math></p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mn>441</mn><mo> </mo><mo>÷</mo><mo> </mo><mo>[</mo><mn>270</mn><mo> </mo><mo>÷</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>7</mn></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>+</mo><mo> </mo><mo>(</mo><mn>17</mn><mo> </mo><mo>÷</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>3</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mo>(</mo><mn>8</mn><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><mo> </mo><mo>-</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>5</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mo>]</mo></math></span><br/>⇒ 441 ÷ [630 + 51 - 6 ]<br/><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mo>⇒</mo><mo> </mo><mn>441</mn><mo> </mo><mo>÷</mo><mo> </mo><mn>675</mn><mo> </mo><mo>⇒</mo><mo> </mo><mfrac><mn>49</mn><mn>75</mn></mfrac></math></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">In ΔABC, AB and AC are produced to points D and E respectively. If the bisectors of angle CBD and angle BCE meet at point O, such that ∠BOC = 63°, then ∠A = ?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>54°</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>27°</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>63°</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>36°</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a)<br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-09073613-7fff-5e77-12a7-ae5c8d03597f\"><img height=\"134\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXeo902wQCfRGEHoDRIXlV84jltOa4Q9XcIKhzJ4QmbAfC_NpKWkGnix5A2mjdkKF82arwgNVS7EovBqvrUt1wGkYiOi8voj8AEnRqi5P0485Cj_sReMwBfE90Q1XoN-_VcVmdWe_g?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"120\"/></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">∠BOC = 90</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">° - <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mo>∠</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">A</mi></mrow><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">⇒ 63° = 90° - <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mrow><mo>∠</mo><mi mathvariant=\"normal\">A</mi></mrow><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">⇒ ∠A = 54°</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">What is the length (in cm) of the smallest altitude of the triangle whose sides are 5 cm, 12 cm and 13 cm? (correct to one decimal place)</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>1</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>0</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>6</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>6</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5, 12, 13 is a pythagorean triplet. So, the smallest a</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ltitude of the triangle is at the hypotenuse.</span><br/><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-b55420c0-7fff-9a7f-f580-a5f3307ed046\"><img height=\"110\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXdj3a1rdKq834Hjgs4MIQJPf-a58zt3i_-BN9uOSgsexGX4NkxJ3qNF9iJWlTwXxHVXGHfhocCWcjob19_LJDww00cTRIuQPEJcVDVuASWTtG7GKMxbzM-KM3ZiJ4-El858tG5T?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"100\"/></strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> × AB × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">BC = <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>1</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac></math> × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">BD × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">AC</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">5 × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">12 = BD × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">13</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">BD = 4.6</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Study the table and answer the question.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The data given in the table shows the number of students studying in four different disciplines in 5 institutes. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: 'Cambria Math';\"><strong id=\"docs-internal-guid-5b47739f-7fff-f29d-21f8-16866d025d5a\"><img height=\"134\" loading=\"lazy\" src=\"https://lh7-rt.googleusercontent.com/docsz/AD_4nXcxQApN_pt0jnFhFjHd8e1zBOmBH3V6zAbrelfucWGQIBOGBLs5bVeY6mlg61FB-muapZCW7X9lxd-zq1JH7HcX6LMT2uKldtrOIMEYc1CIJcjLNERc6_q25MgZuqpsNJRti3N2?key=O7Is54Vj-yjFjOwbq5QaPoMx\" style=\"max-width:420px;max-height:320px;width:auto;height:auto;display:block;margin:10px auto;\" width=\"400\"/></strong></span><br/><span style=\"font-family: 'Cambria Math';\">Number of students studying commerce in institute D is what percent of the total number of students of the 5 institutes?</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>3</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>5</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>1</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>7</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Number of students studying commerce in institute D = 55</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Total number of students of the 5 institutes = 1000</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Percentage =</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> <math xmlns=\"http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML\"><mfrac><mn>55</mn><mn>1000</mn></mfrac></math> × </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">100 = 5.5%</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the INCORREC<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">TLY spelt word. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Censure</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Criticism</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Hellicopter</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Approval</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) Hellicopter<br/>Helicopter is the correct spelling</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the most appropriate antonym of the given word.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Hassled</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Annoyed</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Relaxed</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Worried</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Stressed</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<strong>Relaxed- </strong><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">not worried or tense</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Hassled</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">to annoy somebody</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Annoyed</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">feeling angry or slightly angry</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Worried</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">a small aircraft that can go straight up into the air</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Stressed</strong>-worried and nervous</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>The following sentence has been split into fou<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">r segments. Identify the segment that contains a grammatical error.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The weather / is much / more warmer / than it was a few days before.</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>more warmer</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>than it was a few days before.</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>The weather</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>is much</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) more warmer.<br/>When we do a comparison between two things, we don’t use ‘more’ with a comparative degree (warmer) because it becomes a case of superfluousness(not necessary). <b>Hence,</b> ‘warmer’ is the most appropriate answer.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Sentences of a paragraph are given below in jumbled order. Arrange the sentences in the<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">right order to form a meaningful and coherent paragraph. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A. The festival is named after the Indian Hornbill. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">B. The Hornbill festival is the most anticipated </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">cultural carnival of this state.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">C. Located in Northeast India, Nagaland is a very beautiful and an ethnically diverse state. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">D. The Hornbill is often displayed on the traditional tribal headgears worn during Naga festivals. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>ABCD</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>BCAD</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>ACB<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">D</span></p>",
        "option_4": "<p>CBAD</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) CBAD<br/>Sentence C will be the starting line as it contains the main idea of the parajumble i.e. Nagaland. However, Sentence B states that the Hornbill festival is the most anticipated cultural carnival of this state. <span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">So, B will follow C. Further, Sentence A states that the festival is named after the Indian Hornbill &amp; Sentence D states that the Hornbill is often displayed on the traditional tribal headgears worn during Naga festivals. So, D will follow A. Going through</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> the options, option (d) has the correct sequence.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the option that can be used as a one-word substitute for the given group of words.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">An imaginary ideal society free of poverty and suffering </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Heaven</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Utopia</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Dreamland</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Paradise</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<strong>Utopia</strong>- an imaginary ideal society free of poverty and suffering<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Heaven</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">a place or a situation in which you are very happy</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Dreamland</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">an imagined and unrealistically ideal world</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Paradise</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">the perfect place where some people think that good people go after they die</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the most appropriate synonym of the given word.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Poignant</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Beautiful</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Quiet</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Happy</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Touching</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<strong>Touching</strong>- <span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">that makes you feel sad</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Poignant</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">causing sadness or pity</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Beautiful</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">very pr</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">etty or attractive</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Quiet</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">with very little or no noise</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the most appropriate ANTONYM<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">of the given word.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Fallacy</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Trick</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Truth</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Flaw</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Cheat</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b)<strong>Truth</strong>- the <span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">quality of being true</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Fallacy</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">a false belief or a wrong idea</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Trick</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">something that you do to make somebody believe something that is not true</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Flaw</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">a mistake in something </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Cheat</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">to act in a dishonest or unfair way in order to get an advantage</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the option th<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">at expresses the given sentence in indirect speech.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Raj said to his friend, “Please help me in this task.” </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Raj ordered his friend to help him in this task</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Raj threatened his friend to help him in this task</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Raj said to his friend please hel<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">p me in this task</span></p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Raj requested his friend to help him in that task</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) Raj<strong>requested </strong>his friend to help him in that task (Correct)<br/>(a) Raj <span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">ordered</span> his friend to help him in this task (Incorrect reporting verb)<br/>(b) Raj <span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">threatened</span> his friend to help him in this task (Incorrect reporting verb)<br/>(c) Raj <span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">said</span> to his friend please help me in this task (Incorrect sentence structure)</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the option that will substitute the underlined part of the given senten<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ce. In case no substitution is needed, select ‘No substitution required’.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Fifty litres of milk </span><span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\"><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">are donated by the committee</span></span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> to the orphanage every week.</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>is donated by the committee</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>are being donated by the committee</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>are donated by a committ<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ee</span></p>",
        "option_4": "<p>No substitution</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) is donated by the committee.<br/>We always use a <strong>singular verb</strong> with an <span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\"><strong>uncountable noun</strong></span>(milk in the sentence). However, ‘is’ is a singular verb &amp; ‘are’ is a plural verb. <b>Hence,</b> ‘is donated by the committee’ is the most appropriate answer.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Sentences of a paragraph are given below in jumbled order. Arrange the sentences in the right order to form a meaningful and coheren<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">t paragraph. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A. When it was time to divide the spoils, the lion took one portion for his title as king of the forest.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">B. He took another portion because he was a partner, and yet another because he was the strongest.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">C. He took the last portion because an</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> accident would befall anyone who laid a paw upon it. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">D. Once a lion went hunting with three other beasts. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>DCBA</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>DABC</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>CABD</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>BDCA</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) DABC<br/>Sentence D will be the starting line as it contains the main idea of the parajumble i.e. a lion and three beasts going hunting. However, Sentence A states that when it was time to divide the spoils, the lion took one portion for his title as ki<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ng of the forest. So, A will follow D. Further, Sentence B states that the lion took another portion because he was a partner, and yet another because he was the strongest &amp; Sentence C states that he took the last portion because an accident would befall a</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">nyone who laid a paw upon it. So, C will follow B. Going through the options, option (b) has the correct sequence. </span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the most appropriate option to fill in the blank.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">It was difficult to_____ Gopal to watch a horror movie.</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>confer</p>",
        "option_2": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> persuade</span></p>",
        "option_3": "<p>dissuade</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>consult</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) persuade<br/>Persuade means <span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">to make </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">somebody believe or to do something. </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The given sentence states that it was difficult to make Gopal watch a horror movie. <b>Hence,</b> ‘persuade’ is the most appropriate answer.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the most appropriate meaning of the given idiom.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Sit on the fence</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Create Conflicts</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Protect Something</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Avoid making a decision</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Poke fun at people</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) Si<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">t on the fence- avoid making a decision</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Example- You can't sit on the fence any longer - you have decide whose side you're on</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the most appropriate meaning of the given idiom.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Fair and square</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>By and means available</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>According to the rules</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Beautiful in appearance</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Calm and quiet</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) Fair and square- according to the rules<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Example- The X party won the recently held election in a fair and square way.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the most appropriate synonym of<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> the given word.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Calm</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Joyful</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Cranky</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Clean</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Relaxed</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d)<strong>Relaxed</strong>- <span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">not worried or tense</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Calm</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">not excited</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">, quiet</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Joyful</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">very happy</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Cranky</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">bad-tempered</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Clean</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">not dirty</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the option that can be used as a one-word substitute for the given group of words.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">A dynamic campaign for political, social or religious change </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>Mutiny</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Conflict</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Crusade</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>War</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c)<strong>Crusade</strong>- a dynamic campaign for political, social, or religious change<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Mutiny</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">an act of a group of people, especially sailors or soldiers, refusing to obey the person who is in charge</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>Conflict-</strong> </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">a fight or an argument</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"><strong>War</strong>- </span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">a state of fighting between different countries or groups</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>The following sentence has been split into four segments. Identify the segment that contains a grammatical error.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The visitors complained / at the poor accommodation / they were provided / during the tour.</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>they were provided</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>at the poor a<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ccommodation </span></p>",
        "option_3": "<p>The visitors complained</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>during the tour</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) at the poor accommodation.<br/>There is a prepositional error in the given sentence. The preposition ‘<strong>at</strong>’ after ‘complained’ should be replaced with ‘<strong>about</strong>’.‘Complain about’ means to express one’s dissatisfaction with something. Similarly, in the given sentence, the visitors are showing their dissatisfaction with the poor accommodation provided to them. <b>Hence,</b> ‘complained about the poor accommodation’ is the most appropriate answer.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the INCORRECTLY spelt word.</p>",
        "option_1": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> Subseqently </span></p>",
        "option_2": "<p>Substantially</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>Solicitation</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>Sentimentally</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "1",
        "solution": "<p>(a) Subseqently.<br/>Subsequently is the correct spelling.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the option that expresses the given sentence in active voice.<br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">I am paid weekly by my organis</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ation</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>My organisation paid me weekly</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>My organisation would pay me weekly</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>My organisation will pay me weekly</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>My organisation pays me weekly</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) My organisation<strong>pays </strong>me weekly (Correct)<br/>(a) My organisation <span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">paid</span> me weekly (Incorrect Tense)<br/>(b) My organisation <span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">would</span> pay me weekly (Incorrect Tense)<br/>(c) My organisation <span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\">will</span> pay me weekly (Incorrect Tense)</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the option that will substitute the underlined part of the given sentence. In case no<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">substitutio</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">n is needed, select ‘No improvement required’</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">He </span><strong><span style=\"text-decoration: underline;\"><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">fell over</span></span></strong><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> in studies owing to his illness </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>No improvement required</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>fell for</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>fell out</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>fell behind</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) fell behind.<br/>The phrase ‘fell behind’ means fail to keep up with one's competitors or fail to do something on time. The given sentence states that he failed to keep up with his studies owing to his illness. <b>Hence,</b> ‘fell behind’ is the most appropriate answer. </p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p>Select the most appropriate opt<span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ion to fill in the blank.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">She knew that to apologise would _____ to admitting she had failed</span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>tantalizing</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>tandem</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>tantamount</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>tangible</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) tantamount<br/>Tantamount means <span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">having the same effect or value as something.</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\"> The given sentence states that she knew tha</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">t to apologize would be the same as admitting that she had failed. <b>Hence,</b> ‘tantamount’ is the most appropriate answer.</span></p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><strong>Cloze Test:</strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The first human beings to control fire gradually learned (96)_____ many uses. Not only did they (97)______ fire to keep warm and cook their food; they (98)_________learned to use it in hunting or warfare, to kill insects, to (99)_____</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">_ berries, and to clear forests of underbush so that game (100)______be better seen and hunted. Eventually they learned that the burning of brush produced better grasslands and therefore more games. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Select the most appropriate option to fill in blank num</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ber 96. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>their</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>his</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>its</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>your</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) its.<br/>‘Its’ means of or belonging to a thing mentioned earlier like the fire is mentioned in the given passage. <b>Hence,</b> ‘its’ is the most appropriate answer.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><strong>Cloze Test:</strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The first human beings to control fire gradually learned (96)_____ many uses. Not only did they (97)______ fire to keep warm and cook their food; they (98)_________learned to use it in hunting or warfare, to kill insects, to (99)_____</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">_ berries, and to clear forests of underbush so that game (100)______be better seen and hunted. Eventually they learned that the burning of brush produced better grasslands and therefore more games. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Select the most appropriate option to fill in blank num</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ber 97. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>used</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>use</p>",
        "option_3": "<p><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">prepare</span></p>",
        "option_4": "<p>ready</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) use.<br/>The given passage is about the use of fire for different purposes. <b>Hence,</b> ‘use’ is the most appropriate answer.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><strong>Cloze Test:</strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The first human beings to control fire gradually learned (96)_____ many uses. Not only did they (97)______ fire to keep warm and cook their food; they (98)_________learned to use it in hunting or warfare, to kill insects, to (99)_____</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">_ berries, and to clear forests of underbush so that game (100)______be better seen and hunted. Eventually they learned that the burning of brush produced better grasslands and therefore more games. </span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Select the most appropriate option to fill in blank num</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">ber 98. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>alternative</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>instead</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>well</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>also</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "4",
        "solution": "<p>(d) also.<br/>Also as an adverb means in addition. The given passage states that in addition to its use in cooking food, human beings also learned to use fire in hunting or warfare. <b>Hence,</b> ‘also’ is the most appropriate answer.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><strong>Cloze Test:</strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The first human beings to control fire gradually learned (96_____ many uses. Not only did they (97)_</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">_____ fire to keep warm and cook their food; they (98)_________learned to use it in hunting or warfare, to kill insects, to (99)______ berries, and to clear forests of underbush so that game (100)______be better seen and hunted. Eventually they learned tha</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">t the burning of brush produced better grasslands and therefore more games.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Select the most appropriate option to fill in blank number 99. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>acquire</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>safeguard</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>obtain</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>attain</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "2",
        "solution": "<p>(b) safeguard.<br/>Safeguard means something that protects against possible dangers. The given passage states that human beings learned to use fire to safeguard berries. <b>Hence,</b> ‘safeguard’ is the most appropriate answer.</p>"
    },
    {
        "question": "<p><strong>Cloze Test:</strong><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">The first human beings to control fire gradually learned (96_____ many uses. Not only did they (97)_</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">_____ fire to keep warm and cook their food; they (98)_________learned to use it in hunting or warfare, to kill insects, to (99)______ berries, and to clear forests of underbush so that game (100)______be better seen and hunted. Eventually they learned tha</span><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">t the burning of brush produced better grasslands and therefore more games.</span><br/><span style=\"font-family: Cambria Math;\">Select the most appropriate option to fill in blank number 100. </span></p>",
        "option_1": "<p>shall</p>",
        "option_2": "<p>will</p>",
        "option_3": "<p>could</p>",
        "option_4": "<p>must</p>",
        "option_5": "",
        "answer": "3",
        "solution": "<p>(c) could.<br/>‘Could’ is used for saying that something may be or may have been possible. The given passage states that human beings learned to use fire to clear forests of underbrush so that game could be better seen. <b>Hence,</b> ‘could’ is the most appropriate answer.</p>"
    }
]